SR. JAVA DEVELOPER

Career Overview

Sun Certified programmer of java 1.7(OCA completed) Over 5yrs of experience in Analysis, Design, Development, Implementation and Testing of web based applications using Java/J2EE technologies. Broad experience with Software Development Life Cycle, Software Development Methodologies (Agile) and practices. Extensive experience in developing web based application using J2EE components like Web Services, spring, Spring MVC, Hibernate, Struts, Tiles, JSP, JSTL and Servlets. Extensive experience in using various design patterns such as MVC (Model-View-Controller), Singleton, Session Facade, DAO, DTO in the development of Multi-Tier distributed Enterprise Applications. Experience in developing and deploying applications using servers such as Tomcat, Oracle WebLogic and JBoss, tools such as TOAD and SQL Developer for database development and interaction, using IDE's such as Eclipse, Net Beans. Working knowledge in XML related technologies like XML, DTD, XSD, X-Query, XSLT, X-PATH, XML parsing using SAX and DOM. Involved in all stages of software development life cycle (SDLC). Proficient in writing SQL queries for various analysis and adhoc reports. Excellent problem identification skills through JUnit, Log4j and Ant. Experienced in handling daily assignments and on call supporting production issues. Good debugging and problem solving skills with excellent understanding of system.

Qualifications

- Application/Web Servers Web Logic, Tomcat, JBoss.
- Operating Systems Windows (XP, NT, 2000)
- Databases MySQL, Oracle
- Frameworks Struts, Spring, MVC, Hibernate
- IDEs Eclipse, NetBeans
- Languages Java, HTML, SQL, PL/SQL, Stored Procedures
- Methodologies Agile, Scrum
- Middle Ware EJB, JPA, Hibernate, JDBC
- Tools & Utilities JUnit, JMock, Log4j, ANT, Maven
- VersionControl Tools: SVN
- Web Services SOAP, REST
- Web Technologies JDK, J2EE, Servlets

Work Experience

05/2013 to 12/2014

Sr. Java Developer Jpmorgan Chase & Co. i1/4 Bloomington

- It is a Planning and tracking tool for agile team following extreme Programming (XP) or Scrum
- To summarize the XP planning process, the customers pick the features to be added (user stories) to each development iteration (typically, one to three weeks in duration).
- The developers estimate the effort to complete the stories either at the story level or by decomposing the story into tasks and estimating those.
- Information about team development velocity from the previous iteration is used to estimate if the team can complete the stories proposed by the customer.
- If the team appears to be overcommitted, the set of stories are renegotiated with the customer, customized for LDAP authentication, calculate the effort variance and schedule variance and display in reports for task level and project level.
- Responsibilities: Designed and developed the application using agile Methodology and followed Scrum.
- Involved in Configuration and Usage of Apache Log4J for logging and debugging purposes.
- Used Maven to build the project and JUnit to develop the unit test cases.
- Used Version of control (SVN) for creating the project structure and version controlling.
- Used Quality Center for tracking of all the defects in the various environments.
- Integrated the spring with struts and hibernate frameworks.
- Developed Stateless Session beans which invoke Hibernate database calls.
- Wrote Hibernate Configuration file, Hibernate mapping files and define persistence classes to persist the data into Oracle database.
- Hibernate used as the ORM mapping tool and worked with Hibernate Query Language (HQL).
- Business logic written on the action classes of struts using core java (J2SE).
- Coordinated with the QA team in testing of the application in various environments.
- Created the web UI using Struts, JSP, Servlets and Custom tags.
- Used JSP, JavaScript, JSTL, Custom Tag libraries, Tiles and Validations provided by Struts framework.
- Design and developed UI screens using AJAX, JSP, HTML and CSS.
- Developed the entire application using Eclipse and deployed it on Tomcat Server.
- Implemented it 8n (Internationalization) translating all aspects of the application into different languages.
- Environment: Java 1.6, Eclipse, Maven, Log4j, JUnit, Tomcat, PL/SQL, Restful-services, My-SQL, Struts, Custom tag library, Spring, Hibernate, jsp, jstl, html, jQuery, Ajax.

10/2012 to 04/2013

Sr. Java Developer Jpmorgan Chase & Co. ï1/4 Brentwood

- The application is a distributed Test Automation Tool for creation of Test Cases and test suites.
- Test Cases are converted to a common format enabling them to be executed with a multitude of test automation software (Selenium, QTP).
- The solution consists creation of test cases and suites, a JavaEE Execution engine for broadcasting/distributing test cases for execution bots

- and desktop Execution Bots capable of executing test cases on a multitude of web browsers.
- Responsibilities: Designed and developed the application using agile Methodology and followed Scrum.
- Interacted coordinated with the Design team, Business analyst and end users of the system Developed web application using spring and hibernate Frameworks.
- Design and developed UI screens using Jsp, JavaScript, Html, CSS, jQuery and Ajax.
- Used annotations in spring and hibernate.
- Responsible for configuring and deploying builds on Weblogic application server 10.3.
- Used Eclipse heilos as the IDE for building the project application.
- Used SubVersion (SVN) for creating the project structure and version controlling.
- Used PL/SQL Developer for interacting with the MySQL Database for executing the queries.
- Used Quality Center for tracking of all the defects in the various environments.
- Coordinated with the QA team in testing of the application in various environments.
- Used Maven to build the project and JUnit to develop the unit test cases.
- Environment: Java 1.6, J2EE, JSP, Servlets, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, WebLogic- 10.3, Eclipse, Subversion, Hibernate, Spring.

04/2009 to 03/2011

Java Developer Publicis Groupe Sa ï1/4 Philadelphia

- Project #1: Kohl's Backend Management System Apr 2011- Aug 2012 Description: The Vision of the Kohl's Backend Management
 Console (KBMC) is to provide an interface to manage the database with help of a well-designed UI using the REST-services to save the
 data to the Kohl's Database.
- It has features to manage data only by the registered users such as Wallet Manager and Channel Manager which are created by the admin's form the UI Console.
- Wallet Managers able to manage the data related to offers, products and geo locations where as channel managers able to manage the data related which offer should be given to which channel.
- Responsibilities: Designed and developed the application using agile Methodology and followed TDD, Scrum, pair programming.
- Interacted coordinated with the Design team, Business analyst and end users of the system.
- Designed and developed the project using MVC design pattern.
- Used JSP, JavaScript, JSTL, and Validations provided by jQuery.
- Deployment of Application in the Tomcat Server 6.0 environment using Maven tool.
- Implemented caching techniques, wrote POJO classes for storing data and DAO's to retrieve data and did other database configurations using spring configuration file.
- Involved in Configuration and Usage of Apache Log4J for logging and debugging purposes.
- Used Tomcat Server and Eclipse as the IDE.
- Used Version of control System (SVN) for creating the project structure and version controlling.
- Coordinated with web team and QA teams in smoke tests, load test and performance testing of the application.
- Environment: Java, J2EE, Restful Web Services, Struts, Servlets, JSP, HTML, JavaScript, AJAX, CSS, JDBC, Tomcat, Eclipse 3.6, Mayen, SVN, Log4j, JUnit, Navicat, TOAD.
- The Vision of the Kohl's Content Router (KCR) is to provide an interface to manage and schedule the content delivery for the signage touch points (QR Code/ NFC) in Kohl's stores.
- As high level features KCR will allow its admin s to create KCR users and assign access permissions to KCR features while allowing Signage Managers to create/configure Signage Routers, Content Managers to create/configure Content Routers and Content Owners to create/configure Content Providers.
- A Signage Manager can maintain a Signage Router and similarly Content Manager can maintain a Content Router and Content owner will maintain a Content Provider.
- Signage Managers will be able to define content routes for touch points by binding content routers to touch points and schedule the content delivery.
- Content Managers will be able to update the content routes by binding the relevant content provider and program to the content route.
- Responsibilities: Dessigned and Developed the application using Agile Methodology and followed Scrum, pair programming.
- Integrated business layer using Hibernate with Spring DAO.
- Implemented caching techniques, wrote POJO classes for storing data and DAO's to retreive data and the configuration of database using Hibernate.
- Developed GUI using HTML, JSP and JavaScript for client validations Participated in the implementation of client side and server side programming using HTML, Servlets, JSP, and JavaScript and CSS.
- Used Hibernate annotations to interact with the database.
- Developed the entire application using Eclipse deployed it on the Tomcat server.
- Development of search technology using Ajax.
- Used and Involved in Java Selenium.
- Used PL/SQL, Stored Procedures for handling SQL Server database.
- Used SubVersion for creating the project structure and version controlling.
- Performed unit testing for the service classes and the DAO's using JUnit and assist users in the testing.
- Used Maven to build the project and JUnit to develop unit test cases.
- Environment: Java 1.5, J2EE, POJO, Spring, Hibernate, DAO, Agile, HTML, JSP, CSS, Selenium, Maven, JUnit, Subversion, Tomcat ,MySQL Server.

Bachelor of Computer Science and Engineering India Skills

Agile, AJAX, ANT, Apache, Automation, broadcasting, Business analyst, content, CSS, client, DAO, Databases, Database, debugging, delivery, Eclipse, Eclipse 3.6, EJB, estimating, features, GUI, HTML, IDE, J2EE, Java, Java 1.5, Java 1.6, JSP, beans, JavaScript, JBoss, JDBC, jQuery, LDAP, team development, Log4J, logging, Logic, access, 2000, NT, Windows (XP, MVC, MySQL, My-SQL, Operating Systems, Oracle, Oracle database, Developer, PL/SQL, pick, Programming, QTP, Quality, QA, Router, Routers, Scrum, Servlets, SOAP, SQL, SQL Server, stories, Struts, TOAD, Tomcat, translating, Utilities, Vision, web browsers, Web Servers, WebLogic, written